in our last session we looked briefly at
the Theology and philosophy of Thomas
Aquinas and you will recall he's known
in the Roman Catholic Church as the
Angelic doctor and has been the most
important Theologian I think in in the
second Millennium certainly in terms of
Roman Catholic development but his
thinking at the philosophical level has
impacted not only Roman Catholic thought
but also classical Protestant thought
although in our day there's often a
strong negative reactions against Thomas
I don't share in that negativity with
respect to his philosophical
contributions and we looked a lot at in
our last session at the charge against
Thomas of separating nature and Grace
and of his development of the concept of
natural theology
and I'd like to review that a little bit
more and expand upon it today
the idea of natural theology is a
concept that has been much under attack
in the 20th century particularly from
Protestant theologians
because they have a tendency to see in
natural theology a departure from the
purity of biblical Revelation and too
much of a dependence upon man's unaided
intellect by which he in by
philosophical speculation develops his
ideas of God and so on
but again for Thomas Aquinas he based
his view of natural theology on the
plain teaching of the Apostle Paul in
the first chapter of Romans in which
Paul speaks about a knowledge of God
that is derived through nature
now for Aquinas Aquinas qualified his
understanding of the natural theology
that is available to us by reflecting
upon the cosmos he said that the
knowledge of God that we gain through
nature
is
what he called
uh
incomplete
mediate
and it is analogical
but true
now let's just take a few moments to
look at what he meant by these
qualifying terms I'll leave the
incomplete till it's a little bit later
he argued for what is called immediate
natural theology
meaning by that that the knowledge that
we gain from nature about God
is not
a direct
immediate knowledge by which we would
know God
directly when he talks about immediate
he's not talking about something that
happens
instantly with respect to time but he
means by it the term immediate means
without
a medium
we use the term media today to refer to
the press to television to radio and so
on because those are mediums or media
through which we learn things and so the
term mediate and immediate here has no
reference to time it is a reference to
whether there's an intervening mediator
by which the knowledge is acquired and
so when he speaks of natural theology he
says it's mediate that is we don't get
it directly from God but rather
indirectly that God reveals himself
in and through the creation the psalmist
says the heavens declare the glory of
God the firmament shows forth is Handy
handiwork Paul in Romans 1 speaks of the
knowledge of God that comes through the
things that are made that is through the
creation through the creature
so whatever knowledge of God we have
from nature is a mediated knowledge it
comes through nature itself
uh second of all it is analogical and
I'm going to pass over that for a second
because I want to explore that more
deeply
he says it's immediate
incomplete and analogical and let's look
at the word now incomplete what he means
by that is that the knowledge of God
that we gain through the creation
is not a complete and comprehensive
knowledge of God
it is incomplete
nevertheless
it's true and this was the point he was
trying to make that the knowledge of God
that we gain from nature
though it is not as vast or as deep as
the knowledge of God we get from
scripture
nevertheless it is true as far as it
goes
now why is that significant
well it's significant particularly in
light of today's debates about natural
theology many of the things that are
said about natural theology is that not
only is it inadequate and worthless but
many see it as positively harmful
because any knowledge of God that is
gleaned from nature remains stripped of
so much of the important content of our
understanding of God that is given to us
in the Bible
and so it can give us perhaps
Aristotle's first cause but there's a
long way from an abstract first cause to
the personal redeeming father of Jesus
Christ who is revealed in Scripture
but as I've already mentioned
what was significant for Thomas was
those who had attacked the Christian
view of God
leveled their attack chiefly at the
doctrine of creation
and that's true today that if one is an
atheist the most important item of
Christian doctrine that needs to be
demolished is this item of creation
because if creation can be denied then
the very first teachings of the bib the
biblical record with respect to the
character of God would fall with it
Genesis 1 begins with the affirmation in
the beginning God created the heavens
and the Earth so that if you can attack
the idea of a first cause or of a
creation altogether
then you demolish the very Foundation of
Christian thought
so what Aquinas is saying is simply this
yes nature may not prove the full
content of God that we get from sacred
scripture at least what nature does
yield us
through a rational
treatment of the created realm is enough
truth to stop the mouths of the atheists
and of the Skeptics because natural
theology according to Aquinas clearly
demonstrates that God is the author of
the universe
and though that doesn't tell us
everything there is to know about God it
tells us something that is true as far
as it goes that's what he means when he
says natural theology is incomplete
but
true
and that true as far as it goes is vital
to the historic philosophical debates
that have gone on between various forms
of theism and various kinds of atheism
now
before I come back to the analogical one
let me remind you again what I covered
briefly in our last session
namely that in aquinas's Arguments for
the existence of God the five classic
arguments that he gives he talked in
part about God's being
necessary being and I didn't have a
whole lot of time to develop that but
the technical phrase that was used by
the theologians in the Middle Middle
Ages was the phrase ends necessarium now
that just is a fancy way to say
necessary being
but if you recall
from Anselm and Aquinas there are two
ways in which God is said to be a
necessary being and we need to keep that
in mind because sometimes these two ways
of necessity are confused among people
God is a necessary being
ontologically
according to Aquinas
and
logically
what does that mean to say that God
it has ontological necessary being
is almost the redundancy ontology is the
study of being we've mentioned that from
the very beginning when we looked at the
struggle for understanding reality that
began with thales and through the
pre-socratics and the struggle over
being and becoming that we found in
Plato and Aristotle and so on
so that ontology focuses attention on
the question of being
now what Aquinas and others meant by
necessary being
was to describe a being
whose being is not dependent
derived or contingent
and remember I mentioned the difference
between Supreme Being and human beings
the difference between the Supreme Being
and the human being is a difference in
being
that a human being is dependent
you can't live for very long without
oxygen and without water and without
food and so on so that you have certain
needs that you must have met for you to
continue to be not only that you are not
the cause of your own being
you are derived through the normal
process of procreation you were born you
have a birthday
and you are contingent being meaning
that it's possible at least
theoretically that you didn't exist
there was a time when you were not and
there's a time when you will die and in
between those two polls you will undergo
changes which are all indicators of
contingent being
now when Aquinas speaks about God's
being necessary being he means that God
is Not derived not dependent none can
not uh contingent he is the
unconditional one who has the power of
being within himself
eternally
he didn't get his being from someone
else or something else
and since he has the power of being
within himself it is said that he is
self-existing
I often talk about the two children that
were having a dispute about these
questions and one little boy said to the
other little boy where did that tree
come from
and the other boy said well God made the
tree
well where did that fish come from God
made the fish well where did we come
from well God made us
until finally after this discussion
reached the breaking point the one child
said to the other well where did God
come from
and the other child said God made
himself
and that's supposed to communicate to us
a profound level of insight from a small
child unfortunately
it's an erroneous thought
God did not make himself
nothing makes itself again for something
to create itself would require that it
existed before it was it would have to
be and not be at the same time and even
God cannot
bring himself into being from nothing
the answer is that God is not caused
that in order for us to apply
causal links or a causal chain we do
that routinely when we're trying to
trace the origins of various things in
the world in which we live but sooner or
later you're going to have to come to
that which is uncaused that which has
the power of being in and of itself and
if it has the power of being eternally
in and of itself it cannot not be
that is it's being is of
ontological necessity
and ontologically necessary being is a
being who cannot not be that's the
simple uh explanation for what Aquinas
is getting at now the second way in
which he speaks of necessary being is
logically
through his Arguments for the existence
of God Aquinas was trying to show
that not only is God ontologically
necessary but it is logically necessary
that there be an ontologically necessary
being
because without an ontologically
necessary being
nothing could possibly be now this
presupposes one assumption and that
assumption is
that something exists
that there is something rather than
nothing
so that if something exists anything
exists right now then there never could
have been a time when there was
absolutely nothing because if ever there
was absolutely nothing what could
logically possibly be now
absolutely nothing nice notice I said
what could logically possibly be now I
said absolutely nothing and that's for
this simple reason that if ever there
was a time when there was absolutely
nothing
and now there is something somewhere
along the line something would have had
to pop into existence by its own power
and for something to create itself as we
said is rationally impossible it's a
logical impossibility I know people
speak that way I talked about the
launching of the Hubble telescope and
listening to a very respected physicist
on the radio who said 15 to 12 to 15
billion years ago the universe exploded
into being
and I said whoops
if it exploded into being from what did
it explode
non-being
is this respectable philosopher attract
or physicist trying to pass off the idea
that something came absolutely from
nothing
that would destroy the most important
logical Axiom we have actually he'll
only he'll fit out of nothing nothing
comes but if something is here
then logic demands that something
somewhere
has this power of being within itself
or nothing could possibly be
so for Aquinas he argues that from
reflecting on nature we come to the
conclusion that there is both a
ontologically necessary being whose
necessary being is
logically necessary postulate all right
now let's go then to this word
analogical this is so important
to understand
aquinas's contribution
to the history of theological and
philosophical thought
when he talks about the knowledge of God
that we have as being analogical of
course the word that he has in view
there this is the adjectival form of the
word analogy
now when we talk about analogies we talk
about things that have similarities to
other things
such and such as analogous to something
that means it's like it participates in
certain similarities it's not identical
with it but it's similar to it
Al Aquinas distinguished among three
different ways of speaking
descriptively
what's called first of all the univical
or sometimes pronounced univocal
the second is the equivocal
and the third is the analogical
univiko or univocal language is when a
word is used to describe two different
beings
and the meaning of the term remains
exactly the same
I like to use the illustration of the
word God I'm sorry the word good
we talk about good people
we say that God is good
and we say that our dogs are good
do you have a dog Roger no sir you don't
so you can't help me with my
illustration does anybody have a dog
anyone
I have a dog and my dog's a good dog and
I tell them that every day I see a good
dog and what I what do I mean by that
he's a good dog that he has a highly
Advanced ethical sense
whereby he is impeccable in his morality
no I mean by when I say that my dog is
good I mean by that that
he comes when I call him sometimes
he's house broken he doesn't bite the
mailman on the lake
now when I say that that Fred back here
is a good man
do I mean by that simply that he comes
when I call him
or that he's housebroken whether he
doesn't bite the mailman on the leg
obviously not so that when I describe
two different beings a dog and a human
being and use the same word good I am
not using it in a univitical sense
I don't mean exactly the same thing in
both circumstances
now the term equivocal is where the
meaning of the word
is vastly different
from the beings being described for
example if I said I went to a dramatic
reading the other night and I came back
and said that the narrative was bald
what I mean by that that the story
didn't have hair on its head
of course not
I would mean that something is lacking
just as hair is lacking on a bald head
so drama or Pizzazz was locking lacking
from this dramatic reading so in that
case here the terms differ radically
when applied to two different beings
so you have radical discontinuity with
the equivocal language and radical Unity
with univocal language
and in between those two extremes exists
what
Aquinas calls analogical language
that is language of analogy
and that's the basis upon which we can
communicate with each other and it's
even because though we are all human
all of our experiences of certain
realities in this world do not match
exactly
the same nevertheless there's enough
similarity to your experience and to my
experience that we can communicate in a
meaningful intelligible way
well what Aquinas is saying is that the
language we use about God
is the language of analogy
when the Bible calls God the Father
it doesn't mean by that that he's
exactly the same as an Earthly father
but nor does it mean that the
differences are so vast that the
language is worthless and equivocal and
inadequate
but rather that there are similarities
between God's fatherhood and human
fatherhood and enough similarities to
make discussions and language meaningful
now that's very important because in our
day we're living in a time when some
critics have argued that all language
about God is meaningless
and this is all based on what Aquinas
called the analogy of being
looking to scripture that says we are
created in the image of God we are not
Gods God is not exactly like we are but
we have some point of contact some point
of similarity with God
or we would not be able to speak
meaningfully at all about God and so
that point has been critical in the
history of philosophy that because there
is some similarity between human
beingness and divine beingness there is
some ground there for Meaningful
conversation and communication between
the two